one so thank you thank you for being
here my name is Tim obviously that's how
interactions often begin Leslie we just
have spoken it for a few seconds is you
were the first to join but how do you
feel about being here and perhaps very
briefly just introduce yourself to the
group I'll start I'm Leslie and I live
in Christchurch New Zealand and I hope
you can hear me yeah you will
yeah um yeah I've I I've been interested
to get involved in something where I can
participate I I listen to things and
here are the people talking and having a
good time and I would like to be more
part of something more participatory I'm
not quite sure what else to say at the
moment yeah that's beautiful beautiful
so one way to do this then is when we do
these check-ins so Leslie if you
nominate someone to go next you should
be able to see in the bottom left hand
corner of everyone's picture yeah Ben
Thanks hi I'm Ben I'm speaking from the
UK Scotland in the UK in Edinburgh and
I'm not really sure what to expect and
I'm not really sure what I'm doing here
at picking up from less these words I
think you know listening been listening
and sort of towards participation and
sort of bringing those two things
together maybe that's enough for the
moment yeah nice one I'm in the same
boat hey I don't know what I'm doing
alright she's somewhere next Mike
Michael yeah hello Mika I'm currently
living in Spain but I'm from Slovakia
and I am a medical student but I'm also
studying in I'm also interested in
philosophy and I really admire the the
podcast which Tim is making and I mean
the sense making is really important
especially in these types of such a such
a complex interaction between all the
variables so yeah I'm looking forward to
hear different opinions yeah like I
don't know what to expect but I'm very
happy to be part of this yeah beautiful
Daniel thank you for joining us we're
just sort of going round and briefly
introducing ourselves and how we feel
about being here the consensus is we're
not really sure but we feel sort of
happy to be here and Michael if you want
to choose the next person yeah very
excited to be here it is a bit surreal
I'm listening to your podcast him since
the summer probably and I reached out he
was explaining that I felt this
participatory urge that was like it got
too loud to ignore so it's really really
awesome being here with all of you again
hopefully the audios okay my
connection isn't great but um yeah I'm
just just jazzed be here oh and I'm in
I'm in America on East Coast Pittsburgh
Pennsylvania in the u.s. nice one so
Daniel has joined us and he's now frozen
so maybe he will unfreeze himself I
don't want to take his take his place
here but out of all the people joining
the conversation today Daniel is the
only one that I've met previously there
we go there he is he's back Daniel would
you like to introduce yourself briefly
sure I feel a little on the spot cuz I
just showed up
you are on the stable thank you so my
name is Daniel um I'm currently actually
just finished my undergrad at the
University of Toronto I was studying and
that tells you what you need to know so
good
I actually met Daniel at a conference in
Prague Daniel you frozen by the way if
you can hear me we're still Leo you're
frozen but um I met Daniel at a
conference in Prague a couple years ago
and yeah we've we've had a couple
conversations since then but not for a
long time now and so I was really
excited to see that he signed up to come
along to this at this particular
conference that was that was one of
those places where everyone you meet you
know is jazzed for a conversation as
you're saying Jessica and everybody's
kind of their energy is up you know and
of all the people I met I think Daniel
was someone who sort of intellectually
and just energetically I just locked
into a similar level straight away so
he's actually writing a book with John
Vevey key yeah so he's a he's a
wonderfully interesting guy so yeah okay
alright so it's 1004 we've got the sort
of the next five to ten minutes let's
say just to see if if if
or people come along obviously we might
have technical difficulties as we go
with certain people's internet
connection which is something that we're
all sort of I think have to kind of take
on the chin as it comes along
and we'll just have to trust that the
gods of bandwidth are secretly signaling
to us something so yeah
often what happens with me is at the
beginning of these kind of group things
or the ones I do in person if people I
begin sort of explaining a bit about
what we might do and then extra people
come along and I'm like I'm gonna have
to recap all of that and that might get
that might get a bit boring but I'll try
and be quick about it that's one of the
things about organizing this kind of
thing but I think this this feeling of
not knowing what we're doing is is it's
a really good place to begin from and
I've been thinking a lot recently about
what it is to open space or what is it
to open a frame and often when we begin
with a particular frame that
is so much of what might come from it
and sometimes that's necessary but
sometimes I think as well it's something
to be wary of so you know I aspire in
these kind of conversations for this to
be truly something where where we go and
how we are together is determined by by
each of us you know and how we are
together and not not solely by what I
want to do you know with that being said
I do intend to guide this you know to
some degree so this it's really tricky
balance and it's difficult to articulate
so you know the selection bias I think
is definitely towards people who are
willing to step in to do something that
they're not really sure about and you
know that's exciting for me but we
should probably also note that that
probably distinguishes us from a certain
selection of population straight away
but okay so there's five of us in here
now and there are six other people who
could be here which is which is
interesting to know for the future I
chose a very neutral title for this for
the same reason voice crafting the
moment this is something that we can if
we desire pull apart straight away yeah
what is the moment is there such a thing
as a moment you know we've been here
already with many moments together
how many an infinite we could never or
could we
choose each particular time along the
way I don't think so yet nevertheless
where we are right now is in relation to
the past and the future and so we're
comprised of a lineage of patterns and
we move into the future in a way that is
- led by patterns we expect at least in
part so this is a neutral title because
I'm interested to see whether if we can
gather in such a way and to settle and
tune in and speak what feels to be
called we can begin very tenderly to get
a sense of how it is we came to be here
what constitutes us in being here and
perhaps where we're going and so in that
sense this is something we could
approach from an angle of story as
Daniel is welcome back there we go hello
yeah no worries okay you're muted a
little bit there I think I kind of quite
hear you
but it's good because this is good
basically I'm we're going to be taking
all technical difficulties as as
challenges to overcome from the gods of
bandwidth and connection and if if if a
mere disconnection was to scuttle all of
this then it's not getting anywhere
anyway so please disconnect yourself
again I want it give it to me cool so so
there's about as I was just saying about
six more people to come along and in
about five minutes that will probably
not admit anyone else and we can begin a
sort of a few moments of silence
together and then begin to express and
Daniel I was just outlining that in
proposing a frame for discussion
that is proposing quite a lot and I'm
wary of the frame creating process and
I'm attracted to gathering together in
such a way that can be as aware as
possible of its own framing yeah I'm
just I'm interested in that
knowing that automatically in being here
in this moment so many frames are
already being brought together sort of
come along the patterns which comprise
us over the you know the lineage of our
past and those that we are optimized and
expecting to move into also comprise
this moment and so the practice that we
can experiment with together is one
where we I hope you know I certainly
intend to tune in to what's calling in
to be spoken in me to us here and if we
are able to do that have that open out
appropriately to make sense of what's
around us I spoke while you were
disconnected about this relationship
between the patterns that comprise us
over the course of our history and the
patterns which we are expecting to move
into and how we find ourselves in here
and now in relation to those how do we
feel about that as a quite an abstract
in some sense way to begin but in
another is actually a cool too deeply
tuned in to the here and now
I wonder if that comes across as what is
it to embody a kind of inquiry that is
in principle as I open it as it can be
without being lost you know more
disconnected in abstraction that is
something that I think we can actually
do together if we if we tune in I think
I'll get to feel it as we start talking
together yeah
I like I like some of the things you've
said about the past your the patterns
and and having to you know if we have a
very tight frame we might then restrict
what we bring into the into this
gathering and I'm interested in seeing
what this gathering can produce with us
and I I like that we don't want to frame
it too tightly and and I think we'll
start maybe feeling it a bit and then
hopefully we can talk about it as we
start feeling it with you know right now
I'm just started talking know a little
bit more than I did a minute ago
so I'm looking hearing you all talk and
get a feel for you all
yeah beautiful you're muted still Daniel
but not to resume okay yeah it's
it's an interesting one it's like can be
speaking with my family or in any kind
of gathering the opening the space said
the setting of the scene people have to
willingly step into that we can we can
sit here together and we can talk about
a thing that we're not yet doing
although were indicating you know we
have any sort of an interest in doing it
but it's like a magical thing that
happens where it's like okay we can do
the thing now and then it's and then
it's different it's this weird threshold
thing of accepting invitations and being
voluntary and one's participation and
it's it's so remarkable how in the kind
of truncated nosov communication we
often find ourselves in with with with
various people in our lives we might
even know well can there's like an
invisible threshold that's almost
impossible to step over and it's rare to
it can be rare to find those moments
with each other Daniel so I can see you
here again we've there we go how it can
be here I hope so yes we can hear you
yes yeah so I was using these headphones
with my phone and I just put them
through the wash so I think I've learned
that those broke in the process of being
watched yeah yeah yeah so what I wanted
to comment on was this so having
conversations that require us to push
beyond the boundaries of our framing I
think will require use of metaphor and
narrative if you look at Plato's
dialogues every time he's pushing his
knowledge to the boundaries of something
he always reverts to myth and to
metaphor so not something that I would
like to see employed and to also make it
known into space that metaphor and like
weird analogical things that maybe don't
a hundred percent make sense right now
or like probably very very okay and
exactly what's going to get us to push
into new frames and to sufficiently
reformulate such that we bring into
world
into being in the process of having
conversations yeah beautiful I took the
liberty Daniel of when you disconnected
to introduce how we met and that you're
the only person who I expect to come to
this conversation today who I've
actually met before I let everyone know
that you're currently writing a book
with John Vevey key as well so I spoke
on your behalf to introduce you I hope
you don't mind no those were exactly the
things that I was mentioning anyway so
I'm glad I'm over that for me yeah nice
one cool okay all right so it's now
we're now sort of well into this then
and okay I'll see if I can say a few
things just briefly and then I'll
indicate we'll go into a bit of silence
together I'd say for about a minute or
so and then whoever feels cool to
respond in any way I your you're more
than welcome
I may as well so and from this point hey
I'm in the same boat I'm not looking to
facilitate hands back I'm gonna be it
we're all we're all here together so so
yeah it seems to be the case that well
I'm interested in what understanding
feels like as a movement you know this
dialogical process of of back and forth
that is as well informed by past and
future each of us brings these dynamics
to bear where historical creatures were
also creatures of the future in the here
and now and it seems to me very clearly
that there are perspectives I can take
that are uniquely mine and there are
perspectives each of you can take that
are uniquely yours and that nevertheless
I cannot exist as a unique thing without
being Co constituted by the very
processes which make you and so we have
this from one angle paradox of
this relation between individual and
collective and in an esoteric but deeply
a embodied of the heart kind of way I
have a a hope and in some sense a it
feels like a knowing that in being with
each other in and expressing what is not
just with the voice you know with with
the body with with music with different
forms of expression making art
what-have-you we can in movement engage
in a process of revealing and deepening
our appreciation for what is and that
this process is one that can be
understood as a as a making sense but
also as one that is of a nature that is
feeling and a kind of gnosis where
otherwise analytic or abstract notions
of making sense
don't don't seem perhaps as as relevant
as they do from other modes so maybe
there's elements of the left and right
hemisphere sort of working together here
if you want to think about it from a
McGilchrist sort of perspective and also
that there is this thing we're doing
when we express ourselves and distribute
that expression among each other that
perhaps let's in a bit more of the light
illuminated through each one of our
psyches you know in the patterns that
have constituted us in what we project
towards so
there is a a deep practice here that we
can experiment with and figure out over
the course of the rest of our lives this
is in some sense dipping a toe in the
only other thing I'll say is that
questions which synthesize and deepen
our beautiful things in these practices
I've found but it's not all about asking
questions it seems to me and you know I
encourage each of you to tune in to what
feels call the new to express to trust
yourself in that as well and you know I
think I make so many will not say total
errors but I make many errors myself in
in doing that consistently so it's
really lovely and I'm really grateful to
have you all here and thank you so I'm
going to close my eyes and meditate for
about a minute I'll probably do quite a
simple one where I pay a deep attention
to the in-breath and breathe it in and
then I'll pay a deep attention to the
out-breath as we breathe it out and in
those gaps in between I'll tune into the
totality of the experience in in
consciousness the body the mind feelings
that are difficult to name and let that
be as it is and all the noise of my
doing that poorly and the acceptance
that doing it poorly as part of the
process of of tuning in
so it's breathing in and out and being
attended into the space between I'm
curious how it feels for you to be alive
right now in this time what is alive in
you in this time
something to say and it didn't feel so
much like a calling in and I wasn't sure
there was a threshold but I found a
newness and it felt like it wasn't
enough to recognize a newness and what
was new and it felt like that didn't
name it or capture it and I started
looking for something old and something
that was already present
you
mm-hmm yeah
the difficulty to capture things
yeah it feels to be alive right now
perhaps always there's that tension of
not quite being able to express just
what that is and I wonder how much that
has to do is you know importing a frame
that is already telling me is informing
me that I have to respond to the desire
to name things in a particular way and I
and I think to myself well what is it to
be with each other can we be together
broadly in the world without
acquiring a fixed absolutely nameable
definitive thing around which we can all
point to and go
this captures the aliveness you know
this is what we are and what would it be
like to there have a sense of shared
knowing without needing to capture that
knowing bottler up in a way there are
some things that come up for me
you
Daniel you are muted but this time is
zoom there we go so a lot comes to that
for me as I hear you say that
is that a deep sense of trust which is
perhaps unfamiliar to us would be
required to have that silent sitting
trust with others
so what is it to trust
two things come up for me one is that
you should have an idea of the other
person being someone on the same page I
think that's what it is for people to
trust is that we have some sort of
shared intention and then secondly that
the other person doesn't have you know
in addition to having perhaps a
different intention knowing that that
person doesn't have an intention to harm
you I'm interested
neck's with the rest of you
I think there's there's also an element
of trust in self when you're entering
into something like this which is what
what I'm feeling into I think the you
have that that certain ability to just
talk and trust that you're not going to
say some operating just thing you didn't
mean to which that feels very present
for me right Bruce which then you start
to doubt whether what you're about to
say is truth
which then leads to distrust of self but
but knowing knowing that there's a safe
place to land is a good is a good
starting point if that trust can be
mirrored and the other people who are
participating the dialogue I think
that's helpful I really agree with what
what he said it feels to me as it's the
first thing that Trust is the South is
the is the mirror and I kind of feel
kind of vulnerability stepping into this
uncertainty of not knowing what's coming
which is something I haven't felt before
and it's kind of intense
I want to allow some frigidity in trust
something like a vulnerable
reciprocation but and you know the
reciprocation I'm not sure captures the
multidimensionality of what I'm one
thing to convey certainty or a sureness
or surety I can a landing or a grounding
in trust but I want to convey a space
for fragility in that as well yeah when
you talk about fragility and I'm
thinking what what we're coming up for
me in the last thatis I am like I've
been excited to come here and I really
want to do something and then I noticed
the part of me that doesn't want to be
here that kind of wants to to back off
and that doubts that what I'm saying is
is valuable like that's sort of sitting
there as well like I know I've been in
conversations with people where
something amazing happens
so I know I can be a participant of that
um but equally I know there's ways in
which I shut myself down I hear one of
you say something let her go maybe we're
supposed to talk like that and so in a
way I just want to bring forward the
part of me that doesn't that's afraid to
bring myself forward and it's looking
for each of you two to either um tell me
what to do or to react to like oh I
won't I don't want that and those are
sort of intimacy patterns I've got and
you know sorry
yeah I just want it's good to just bring
myself forward as well and not just
listen but I I knew I do tend to
sometimes just listen and yeah it's a
good challenge that no one here is
dictating what we have to do something
that comes up for me there is needing to
develop a trust in following and a trust
in leading and then a trust in making
that transition so perhaps Leslie
there's part of you that feels you are
you know you can be comfortable to sort
of just sit here and being told what to
do but that part of you that is perhaps
a little unsure of taking more of a
leading role you've really brought that
forward and I think I think quite a
beautiful way you've sort of just sort
of named it and gone all right I'm
bringing you along your coming here we
go yeah it's guides and it's such an
interesting thing it makes me think you
know I like to dance and it's is such a
challenge to make for me at least the
switch and orientation towards or am i
leading right now as soon as you ask
yourself you know I might meant to be
taking a more leading role here it can
often take you a bit out of the flow and
then so there's a sort of like what kind
of circuitry or how do we yeah yeah some
beautiful things here Ben you mentioned
before this notion of reciprocity and in
fragility could you say some more things
about how you how you mean those words
in this context
I'm not sure whether I can be I think I
was responding to a question that I felt
invited to inquire into which was what
might it feel like to trust as if I knew
and maybe the first image was dyadic
that it would be to be interest with
someone else and that felt limiting and
so I wanted to open that and when I see
to trust as a sort of a surety certainty
it feels too bright so I wanted to
preserve it with something more living
which I called fidelity I am reminded of
the word faith and of the Living God in
who one must have faith this description
you're giving very much sounds to me
like that relationship of faith
should-should faith then have some
fragility to it
God is want to solve his problems the
genocide very often so yes I think there
is a uncomfortable awareness of the
fragility of human being in any act of
faith yeah I'm reminded of the line in
the Bible and I'm terrible at quotes but
it goes something like jesus said it
even at one point he said
probably said thou in there somewhere
but he said God why have you forsaken me
so there's there's that even God's Son
God himself in some in some way losing
faith in himself yet also carrying
through the action yeah some sort of
threshold it's like we there comes a
point where where we are jumping you
know step step step
well here we go the inertia I'm jumping
I like that you use the jumping
reference there brings to mind the fool
tarot card was precisely the character
who jumps in faith and we don't really
know what lies at the bottom of the
cliff off of which he jumps just have to
hope that it's for the best
but his fragile frame could be revealed
if rocks lie below hmm that's very those
make the exact same image and had been
earlier in fact thinking of the fool and
thinking of how on the the rider-waite
deck there is that dog he sort of
yelping at the fool sort of seemingly to
say don't jump but then there's a sense
perhaps that that the dog could could
sit down and curl up a little and let
and let that moment happen relax it's
okay mm-hmm you let the ego curl up and
get off your heels for a second and like
that reading of the role of the dog in
that image I was thinking lastly about
what Tim mentioned did their archetypal
Jesus and his lost days and it's it
seems to be really powerful that even
the God himself incarnated in the human
body kind of admitted uncertainty and he
accepted it when Satan couldn't
understand him tempting him with all
this power and he just assumed dying as
an ordinary man ordinary criminal at
that time and just like
people were hitting him hitting him and
he was just like accepted it but I think
it was something he would kind of
predict it was a very big uncertainty I
don't know I think it's like very good
kind of sarcasm like a joke that you're
the sons are killing the father which is
not doing anything with it he could do
what he decides not to because he wants
to human experience and all the Hohner
ability which is yeah I like that
that um makes me think that even if you
have power to put up defenses against
the fragility of human existence
sometimes you have to submit to that
process so that everybody involved can
learn from it
it strikes me how high the stakes are in
that game you know how can feel as
though sometimes we are climbing we're
climbing here or walking up a hill is
some loose metaphor to maturing taking
on responsibility having people that
depend on us having covenants we enter
into that if we were to break them would
have real consequences and seems that
the more we
a tame rightful responsibility the more
we can damage those around us if we let
that down and that's sparking em for me
because of that connection with this
fragility of faith
and this notion that well we we build
and build and what happens then when we
have amassed a certain amount of energy
how it's like how how to is it to
dissipate that correctly like what if
because what if we're scared of taking
that next step right what if we scared
of taking that next step because of well
what will happen if we if something
if we make a mistake
but then if we don't take a step and we
just begin to hold on tightly there's a
sense in which we're disconnected so I I
was just feeling really being struck by
the the that this that this dynamic it
feels deeply true to me I don't think it
ever leaves us you know I can have a
present where I just wanted to clarify
the dynamic of like faith and fear that
you're mentioning is not the dynamic
that's always present yeah I think we
could use those words yeah oh it's you
it's one that can it's it's like a it's
like one that continually come back
again yeah the faith and the challenge
to it you know it's a weird thing to
sometimes part of us wants to feel like
you know this is just a challenge that
once I meet I don't have to face again
you
is there something tires
about that what's on the other side of
that tiredness how can we be how can we
is just coming out of faith isn't it how
can we have faith in keeping a faith
it's it kind of reminds me of the of the
I don't believe I know which which is in
my opinion kind of good the way to cope
with with this uncertainty it can kind
of be dangerous because assuming
something is in knowing is even like
transcending the state of faith we put
in it but I think it can it can create
something something really beautiful and
enhance our potentiality into stepping
in unknown air and much greater sense
than we really could rely on the faith
itself
something I'm I'm wondering whether I'm
probably stepping back a bit um but when
we were talking before about trust and I
was talking about wanting to hear each
of you instead of feeling to you and
what I notice is that and you were
talking Daniel about metaphor being an
important aspect of doing um something
to me it's tying tying what we're
talking about which is kind of slightly
abstract and archetypal with what with
us as specific people like when I hear
someone talking about the fool or
something but we relate it to ourselves
and our own particular stories I can I
can see it in a way that I can't track
when we're just talking about the images
themselves then um you know so I feel
like in a way what I'm bringing into
today um you know when you talked about
how we're feeling in this moment and I
felt this very intense sadness and um
pessimism which I'm not you know I was
feeling excited when I first came in and
and I'm afraid of being critical I'm not
being critical but I want to hear who
you are and and then I can relate that
to those really important images that
you were all bringing up which is
wonderful but I can't I find it hard to
trust you all until I know who you are I
know how that relates to you to the the
nitty-gritty specifics of your life what
you're what you struggling was at the
moment or what you were excited by at
the moment
whatever I hope that makes sense yeah
that makes perfect sense and I'm very
happy to hear you bring that up
I think rounding things and the
particulars of our lives is very
important and much more accessible for a
lot of people as well so let's see yeah
I feel like I can bring an example from
my own life right now in where this sort
of leap of faith and the fool character
is very relatable at this moment so I'm
writing this book with a professor of
mine IQ of T and I'm really struggling
because I feel that I'm just not at all
qualified to be writing this I'm trying
to tackle the subject of enlightenment
which is huge and every day I have to
take breaks and writing this and I have
to be like Who am I to be writing this
book you know what authority do I have
to be writing about enlightenment good
finding that's very much a struggle but
I also at the same time have this
awareness that I know that once it's
done it's probably going to be very good
I do have a lot of trust in my writing
than my scholarship so I have these
conflicting sides of me and really all
that I can do right right now because
I've already like committed to deadlines
and I've committed to this project is to
just leap into the project and just kind
of hope that it all falls out of me so
that's where this dynamic has been very
relevant there's definitely a lot of
fear a lot of anxiety but um yeah I feel
like embracing the fool right now is the
best thing that I can do for actually
carrying this out even though I have all
these inhibitions that are like dogs
perhaps barking at me like the dog at
the foot of the fool I'm trying to
distract him from the thing that he
knows he has to do that brings
say also also lending that that sense of
importance in the project if there was
no one if there was no dog working at
your heel - there would maybe be lacking
the sense of this is not just some
William you know there's an importance
and the greatness to it I suppose
hmm yeah I think that's a good way of
putting it importance in the graveness
and Leslie's I'd like to hear you look
like you had a response as well I'd like
to hear if you something yeah I was just
saying that when you told me who told us
about your project
I can relate it to the fall you know I'm
sure we all have a relationship to that
idea of being caught between you know
the call - to some adventure or some
challenge and then the things that were
held back by and just that dynamic
battle between these different aspects
and and so you're bringing that specific
story about your life brings that to
life for me and it's just you know I
just wanted to acknowledge that really
makes a difference for me in them
getting excited about the topic hmm
right yeah I appreciate you bringing it
back down to earth because I
particularly have a hard time sort of
getting lost in abstractions so I like
it when other people's signal to me when
I tend to be doing that so that I can
come back with a little bit
yeah well a story then about me is that
I feel I feel like the the intensity in
switching between high abstraction and
the well the thing is for me that the
high abstraction feels deeply in my body
and or at least I feel connected to it
and so sometimes it can be perceived as
being just in the head and then I can
feel it's quite a challenge because
someone can be saying to me you know oh
well what do you do when someone tells
you you're all in your head it can be
quite isolating and trapping and I'm not
and that's not what's happening here but
how that relates in my life is that I'll
my disposition is to be quite intense
between the abstraction and part of me
really wants to just drop it down and
swear and joke and be be stupid in a way
to line up with this idea about the fool
and where I find myself sometimes is in
situations where the the the feeling of
making those leaps maybe isn't allowed
so if I'm recording a podcast or maybe
even a conversation like this I feel
tension between the fool and
holding some other sort of ground that
is a bit more serious and I
sometimes I what holds me back is the
fear that if I was to be a bit more lewd
or be a bit more disagreeable in the
humor that it might actually alien a and
East and destabilize in a way that isn't
conducive to building what I want to
build this dynamic of the fool and then
what are we saying is on the other side
of things the fool and the the the dogs
that are sort of maybe barking you to
stop that that tension is is one I feel
quite a lot because I I'm scared that
those dogs in me might be barking for a
very good reason you know what I mean
so a character that your share made me
think of is the trickster
the trickster he doesn't really care so
much about what other people think
he's very happy to engage in a world
breaking process I like to call it to be
a bit lewd into she had her people's
expectations to initiate the shift into
sort of a new way of thinking about
things so yeah that was I don't know if
I have much more else to say it just
seemed like a very relevant connection
to mention hmm I wonder when is the is
there a okay so okay so sometimes let's
say it's 2:00 a.m. in the morning and
I've been up a long time or maybe it's
4:00 a.m. in the morning maybe I've
smoked a bit of weed earlier on and I'm
sort of I'm sort of toast you know I
find myself in a mirror and I might be
improvising some voices almost having a
dialogue with myself and it's the kind
of thing where if I was to start doing
that now and post videos people be like
whoa what what the is this do you
know like what this is not what I
expected from this guy that was like
talking all polite and talking about
philosophy and stuff and that is that
I've always been like that
both those sides always the
philosophical but then also the stupid
and it's very difficult for me to bring
those together but part of the reason
why I like what would be an interesting
question out of this then is that is how
cuz because when you break the world you
know I I'm not interested in I'm
in breaking a world for the sake of
hurting you know I'm I'm interested only
in breaking if
what if we can fall together in a way
where in some sense connection is
maintained and we realize ourselves in a
new ground together so I wonder if
there's a distinction between breaking
to exclude and isolate and breaking to
reveal deeper connection I mean that's
what the apocalypse is like
etymologically the apocalypse is the
revelation and then in the Christian
apocalypse a revelation of John the
point of the book at the end is it ends
with a sentence something like this like
let think we can continue to be wicked
and let the good continue to be good and
like every one will every one is good
will come out of the other end more
connected and more whole and then this
whole event will serve himself correct
our relations and all of this so just
sort of have faith in that world
breaking process so that distinction is
very much explicitly there in like the
apocalyptic traditions the biblical
traditions and I also think so one of my
favorite characters is Lucifer and I
think that Lucifer is also very much
this kind of character who is perceived
as being malicious and trying to destroy
the world out of some angered vengeful
kind of motive but if you look at not
just what's canon in the biblical stuff
because Lucifer isn't even a canonical
character anyways so there's not really
a good reason to do that his myth
he's identical to the myth that we get
of this angel called Sophia and how the
Gnostics the early Christians who were
deemed heretical by the ones who became
northa DOX they had this view of Sophia
which was remarkably similar to the
Lucifer myth of the fallen angel but in
that version of the myth the God who
like condemns everybody and throws Adam
and Eve out of the garden are he's like
a a tyrant who has a served power from
this Divine Principle above him and so
in that
relative to that particular frame that
be that Creator God sets up the snake in
the Garden of Eden and there's Lucifer
character is like an evil thing but then
once the act of breaking the world is
accomplished then there's this
revelation that oh actually things for
this other way the whole time and
everything was for the good so that's
sort of what stands out to me is like
the best archetypal representation of
that sort of reframing you think
something's initially frightening and
add but at the end of it once everything
goes through its process of
transformation you reframe the entire
history of the system to say oh actually
this other thing was true the whole time
I think that's a very powerful and
important role that trickster characters
play and to bring it into a little bit
more of a personal kind of thing this is
one of the things that I really like out
of like a heavy metal and that kind of
really abrasive music is often they're
using this kind of satanic imagery to
engage in this process of Revelation to
show that the symbols are perhaps a
little bit different than you thought
they were this whole time see I find
myself carrying that out a lot in the
art that I create and in the music that
I create I like to really sort of go the
extreme end be I'm working on a song
right now which it'll probably change
into something else but this is
interesting similarity between like
Lucifer Satan and Christ where depending
on who framed them they all kind of
collapse into the same thing and at the
end of the book of Revelation Christ
refers to himself as the bright and
morning star which is the epithet that
we associate with Lucifer the song that
I'm writing takes a bit of a playful
approach say that Christ is
cross-dressing as Lucifer at night to
like I don't know go sleep with
everybody and like peruse the town
there's one line where I'm like who
isn't your sheep sort of bringing some
weird bestiality references in there so
it's a really sort of abrasive like
frame shattering kind of song but it's
like so extreme and so absurd but you
just can't take it seriously and I was
having some conflict myself I was
talking to some friends about writing
the song and you know I consulted some
Catholics to like really be careful
about blasphemy and that kind of thing
and sedimentation is so so how could you
yeah I think I think I don't know if you
can't be careful I think that is
blasphemous I thought I you can pull it
back from there right well my friends
perspectives was that our understanding
a blasphemy comes from the Protestant
way of thinking about things where you
know only the text is what's going to
get you to God and so any deviation from
the text is bad but from a Catholic
perspective a narrative experimentation
is fine so long as it is
promote vice so broquet on that front
but you have another friend of mine I
was talking to I was like yo I feel
kinda weird about this is like yeah the
language is very extreme like I call
Christ a and I don't know if I
should do this but they were like not
man like you should really just embrace
it because like obviously this is like
not serious because how can anybody take
this serious so you should just like
jump into it where it fully hmm I'm
quite interested in there's a couple of
things that I noticed I mentioned in
this idea of a negative aspect of
ourselves that um some of us have been
talking about that actually might have
some valuable things to share and so
like Tim you're talking about the
abstract part and this is more rougher
and you know um ruder parts and that
when you talked about those parts of
yourself you know that something else
came out of you that that's a bit less
managed and a bit more spontaneous
something and and then similarly Daniel
when you're talking about um the music
your writing and everything and just
going into those and provocative ways of
expressing it's something really live
lively by that so and so I'm thinking
both in terms of that idea like we could
when you were talking Daniel I sort of
had this image of these galloping horses
and just there's some amazing trains of
thought and we could go along with the
train of thought
but also I'm interested in what each of
us are thinking you know that whole idea
of the negative aspects that actually
hold valuable gifts and I think that's
quite a useful thing for us as a group
to look at because we could go along and
riff on a whole lot of stuff which would
be interesting in itself but in terms of
an actual group experience you know it
just seems there is a bit of a theme
around the negative or the or the these
opposing opposites or something and I
just curious what we each have enix
you know how we each relate to that idea
and if if anyone's interested just so
that we've got something we're sharing
that's kind of equivalent or something
please in my situation toast okay so we
got like real strong current in
measurements here in Spain like you
cannot live or you're not supposed to
leave your house and stuff and I got
stuck in the mountains and in that
environment I got three weeks there just
observing the nature and it really made
me appreciate certain spiritual aspects
which which I was not really in touch
with my being and kind of I felt like
very powerful but in the context of my
grounding I kind of lost grounding and
came back here to Madrid it was like I
felt lost I was like what should i do
like there is the colleague of the anima
but I still didn't work with my shadow
and it can be dangerous if he if he
start to build a tower without having a
firm firm basis because it can fall down
work very easily so they kind of
temptations and callings from from
topics which which I kind of I'm very
interested in and I would like to devote
more time and see but it was still the
reality of my my studies and my career
calling me which are right now for me
not the priority at all and as we are
kind of disconnected in this quarantine
or microcosm becomes like much more real
than when we are in the social
interaction which are kind of signals of
of waking us up from our inner dreams so
this kind of kind of challenging for me
to kind of find this this Brown began to
to face the real issue of
hmm so it
between building a tower and then having
the foundations well enough put so that
you can build that being in relationship
with these themes of present seeing the
shadow so presumably in this context
that would be well I mean I think I'm
building one foundation but actually I'm
not aware that this part of me that's
also bringing something else so I can
start building start building and then
whoops I've been also building something
in its gonna have the thing fall down
and then there's also a piece in there
about the importance of engaging with
each other speaking to each other social
interaction as a way to wake up and
realize what else we're bringing and
then perhaps that links up with I think
Leslie may be part of your initial
motivation for seeking to have us to
draw out what are some of our how do
these concepts relate to us in real life
so that we can well because you how can
how can we be trusting of each other
unless we have an understanding of who
we are in terms of how we're living and
the stories we're living out and so then
the importance of this relationship both
between the the modeling and the
abstraction and then how that's being
embodied and then maybe having that as a
kind of opponent processing which may
help ensure or ensure it's a bit too
strong but may help us bring more in to
the foundation making that can allow for
something to be stronger that we build
together so that's what I'm synthesizing
from some of the expression we've had
here I'm conscious that Leslie you made
the ask that we each maybe share
something about this dynamic how we can
be sometimes opposed in ourselves how we
relate to this idea of the fool in our
own lives so I am conscious of opening
that up because I think
Jessica and Ben you haven't had the
opportunity to express that yes if you'd
like to please please go ahead
I can I can take the baton on this one
I've actually The Fool has played an
important for a mythological role for me
over the last few months it's really
interesting that this discussion went
there I am also currently at that moment
of everyday job which is in the travel
industry I do marketing for the travel
industry travel industry is not faring
so well so now comes the opportunity to
see what's next but
Tsang like you or you do this but also
feeling as if I don't really have a
choice there's a certain a certain pool
that then you know I guess Jessica can I
ask you just to restate that we lost you
there for a second this what this this
pool between so on the one hand
obviously the copywriting the marketing
I know copywriting from the message you
sent me that's in a difficult spot now
because of the travel industry blowing
up what's the pull on the other other
side of that I think that's a part we
missed right and I'm not sure I
necessarily know either
I I before the copywriting life I was
and always envisioned myself as writing
for money
and then as soon as money came in it
became a very challenging you know
situation so now I'm feeling like I need
to return to that side but feeling as
though I failed the first time so now
I'd be taking it a leap once again and
distrusting that something you'd come
out of it but then also sort of more
amorphous lis almost important is that
that individual creative impulse the the
co-creative impulse is very strong but
feeling like I didn't have the
co-creators if that makes sense yeah
yeah that makes sense so it's like it's
weird isn't it because when we when we
write for money doing copy writing when
we work in the world there is a sense in
which it's I mean it's a co-creation of
a kind right but it's a co-creation
where there's your the input the sort of
motivation for being there an imperative
to be there it's got a whole lot of
framing that's been brought along as
baggage and there's a sense that that's
not actually I mean familiar though
that's not actually anchored into the
the essential aspects of us or the
ultimately life oriented aspects of us
as they wish to as realize themselves
now how that impulse wishes to realize
itself now and so there's something for
me at least I've always had to withhold
in that process and it's interesting
that the move to co-creation the
interest in co-creation for you is is
something that it's particularly coming
up there as well because it's that we
can retreat to ourselves and do and we
can write and we're always informed by
other people of course anyway and so
there is that sense of dialogue even
within self but but but seeking to go to
to write with others really again but to
have that process be grounded in such a
way
is more enabling of the expression of
something more life oriented
fundamentally in a way that's more in
touch more connected with that creative
post which is in principle the whole the
essential spark of that co-creation to
begin with yeah that's definitely a very
interesting tension okay well I am want
to stay connected to my experience while
I'm speaking and so in answering the
question about polarization or negative
aspects of my life I want to be able to
speak in a way in which I feel like I'm
bringing that here rather than taking
myself somewhere else and there's
failure would be I would see failure as
a kind of a negative aspect and I think
in terms of polarity it's an established
story I have you know what would it be
like to fail at failing here if if I'm
starting out from a position of wanting
to be in dialogue in a way which goes
beyond representing or at least goes
beyond representing representation and
can begin to feel like or look like or
invite or participate with others in in
something else
so that at the risk of
[Music]
stopping the risk the risk is stopping
if it's if it's not possible and that
but and I'm not sure whether that's
giving any substance to an individual
shadow or whether that gets close to
naming what you know could could be a
collective sigh though here in you know
in this moment if you know if there is
one I'm not sure whether that answers
your question I don't I I think we all
have a different way of approaching the
question I'm interested in in your
wanting to talk about and the different
polarity or something right here which
is interesting and and possibly and when
you talked about the group shadow I
guess every group has has things they
they bring out easily and other things
that it kind of get lost and I think of
those as like the orphans and I'm
interested in always interested in who
the orphans are or you know who's being
what's being ignored or who's being
ignored that's always been a role I
played in my family of who isn't
speaking or who isn't able to speak or
who isn't what's being left out in them
it's a great thing to ask any time
because I guess it relates to that whole
thing of what does the bit in me that
I'm not letting out when I'm not even
what bit and me do I not find valuable
here like I want you to you all to think
I'm intelligent maybe but I'm afraid to
bring out my stupidity or my ignorance
or my I don't know what you meant or you
know all that kind of thing because I
want to be Intel
jintan and and treat you all as
intelligent people and you know so yes I
think it's a really interesting thing to
ask I think Ben there's I was I'm I
think I'm what you said it's fascinating
I think so I'm gonna step into seeing if
I can synthesize a bit of it and I 9 I
know that I'm gonna miss a lot you know
but I what I one thing that I took from
it was a movement actually after the
sharing of some individual perspectives
and movement are bringing us back
actually into into towards again opening
into collective expression in in a
slightly different form and the the the
conflict or the opposition or the that
you referenced I think came through a
lot with this notion of blocking what
are we
so I so so that there's this interest in
expressing participating in such a way
that somehow transcends the
representation of representation and
what you may be bringing to the process
and what we all may be bringing to the
process which is blocking us from from
just that leaving out a lot am I am I
getting at some of the notes of that
expression here yeah yeah I think so
yeah so we've covered a lot of ground
home like we have we've present some
profound notions and also Express
difficulties we have or the sort of
ongoing integration processes we are
experiencing in relation to some of
those notions we've present so from
faith to trust to building foundations
upon which we can construct and notions
of isolation and shadow and and also as
an undercurrent something I mentioned at
the beginning that much of this is to
the stakes get higher and higher and we
have to be willing eventually to jump
and in some sense you give up the stable
ground we're on anyway
so so actually I'm feeling okay so so
I'm feeling that urge then to step back
a little bit as well because in some
sense what we're doing here together
we're having a we're having a
conversation it's taking place in a
certain period in time and while there's
things being brought in and it has a
dynamic to it eventually the record
button and the stop button will happen
go and then we will each be in the four
corners of the world and our experience
will continue and so there's a sense in
which the continuity between this and
the rest of our lives is itself maybe as
relevant in terms of to these notions of
faith as the as are the ways we conduct
ourselves in this conversation in terms
of so so maybe well I'm what I'm trying
to say is that we
don't think at least I'm not seeking to
achieve achieve a thing you know that if
there's a if there's some meaningful
continuity I can take from insight it
generated here into my life or at least
it's like almost what happens after this
is in some sense as important as what
happens in it as well
maybe I'm just kind of stepping back and
opening up the frame even more maybe as
a way to in some sense reduce pressure
you know we don't we don't have to do
anything sort of and maybe in that that
is somehow helpful you know I have so
many different
how to go into these things it's it's
but I also
um I'm want to be careful about
specifying the thing as well it's like I
wish says like so much like it has to be
kept blurry from myself
it's very hard to know what frames we're
playing in but you know what I mean
maybe this conversation part of many
other frames you know I know excuse me
for all that is something that comes to
mind there is some often when I'm having
a good conversation we're either in one
place like like I live in Christchurch
New Zealand so I'm with a group of
people in Christchurch talking and we're
talking about something of relevant
local relevance or maybe I'm talking
with a group of people about a topic you
know like we're interested in in
engaging about some aspect of you know
how to let's say how to live in the
current moment of the covert pandemic
and there's something of
the topic or the locality that arranges
us together and then we have our
dynamics together but the we're held by
the reason why we're there which is to
talk about a topic or or to get
something done like at where I work
contains at work and so we're talking
about that and it's an interesting one
here where the reason why we're here
what we all come from different
countries and the reason why we're here
is kind of to explore what this is and
which is very different from a normal
conversation or Mille that's a dumb word
but a conversation I'm used to having
which is normally where there's
something about the way it's held
together that's important to it or the
or I'm with a group of people that care
about me and I care about them and the
caring holds it and even though you may
not be talking about that it still holds
it and so I mean it's it I'm interested
in the fact that we're all from
different countries and what's holding
us yeah like yeah I realize I'd like to
feel held I'd like to feel held by
people caring about me or at work I like
that I'm at work and I met her I I
matter to the people at work because I'm
valuable to them and there's something
about when I feel held then something
come come out and maybe more than some
people I that's quite important to me in
order for me to for the fullness of me
to come out and so I'm interested to
know how how you all find it coming here
without that
a place or a shared project I guess this
is our shared project but it's it's a
bit different for me it was like it felt
like starting in a very for me
personally special situation where where
I was kind of guided by intuition which
is not really something common in my in
my daily life so it was very noble for
me but then we went like going more more
to the concrete and there I kind of like
felt more more disconnected from the
moment so I felt like I was not just in
a moment well but I was presenting the
timescale of my context so that kind of
brought the ideation which was about
what's he going to stay what you're
going to say instead of just kind of
experiencing it and flowing so yeah I
really loved the the beginning dynamics
it was it was very very noble and very
powerful for me
me I didn't find much of a jump coming
into a space like this but I suppose I
was framing it as a conversational
environment I'm very used to having so I
know Tim is an intellectual friend we
like similar topics we talk about
similar things in similar people so I
think I had a bit of an expectation
about what sorts of things to expect
coming into this and also the whole
shtick about like meeting making and
sense making is something that is
something I think about all the time so
I feel perhaps parity and he's very
natural in this space it doesn't seem
very different from a lot of spaces that
I find myself in so yeah that hasn't
really been as a novel an experience for
me but it is interesting seeing like
where everyone else is coming from all
of the very different sort of variables
that are coming in from everybody
then from you I'm getting the vibe that
I get when I've been to circling
practices you're very concerned with the
here and now of the present moment
dynamic between us and Leslie you're
bringing a lot of interpersonal care and
connection kinds of things so it's cool
to see how everyone is contributing to
what's emerging here which I think Tim
might have bigger point yeah yeah yeah
look I mean the elephant in the room in
some sense is that this conversation
began
I think Daniel you might have been
absent from when I began to make this
point although I think I referenced back
to it to do with this this this paradox
of framing because on the one hand I'm
sort of opening us into a peer-to-peer
discussion where where where we have
been
continually pointing about we're doing
going is this like oh it's changing now
are we
is everyone speaking or are we leaving
things out or who are we away from this
conversation what's happening in this
conversation it we we are pushing out at
the frame in various ways while also
feeling into it like that but there's a
sense in which of course is that I did
send these invitations and I did open a
space right and their coordination point
even though I think it's I mean I would
I would argue it's it's deeper than what
I said tried send it to me but I have
sent invitations
I've been some sort of conduit for the
gathering and you know I do have
intentions you know this to me is
[Music]
something that is it's partly an
experiment but not one that I'm not
holding myself to account for with
respect to the care it's not something
I'm being flippant about but it's an
experiment so far as I don't know what
will happen and I'm interested to learn
and I have done some things in order to
set certain variables you know and it
relates to this project and the project
relates to something deeper than the
project at least that's the hope and for
me there's a kind of sense of continuity
in terms of my projections into the
future that might be slightly different
from each of you here as
well I sent out the invitations so and
we met through the coordination of that
so I feel partly cool then Leslie in
response to your kind of in response to
your point I feel as though you know
there are so many things I could say
about what I what I am hopeful that
something like this can eventually
achieve and this is a multi-decade
multi-century project that truly and
it's it's one you know almost risks
every step of the way being a forlorn
attempt to tune into a solution making
process to some of the deepest
existential risks and potential
tragedies we face because in some ways
we
different not us here although we are so
different I'm mentioning there are
people who have very powerful whether
it's religious or ideological commitment
that would see them in a certain
environment taking action that would be
quite radically other rising to another
group of people we can come into
conflict with each other
whether you know whether that's
piggybacking on our base survival needs
and identities or some other kind of
higher order ideology all these various
ways we can come apart and are coming
apart mixed with the power we have to
enact that separateness is such that it
seems to me we can do more we can
unleash more suffering that might be
necessary so what is it to be in such a
way that can be open to genuine
transformative communication that that
encourages our tuning into a sense of
care and courage and love for the
frame that you cannot name in such a way
that extends until the very last the
hand of well an invitation to dance so
so this such a grand process and and I
and I am very hesitant to bring in many
of the terms and names and various
frames
I might personally bring to kind of
intellectually make sense of part of
that but it that's nothing if there's
not also this continued tuning in and
feeling into where we are as people
together and that is something that just
takes it just takes time and so we have
this coming in and moving back and
coming in and moving back and and I
think that we've seen some of that
happen beautifully well I think you've
done that beautifully well Leslie and
one thing in finally you know I'll say
is that I'm not this is not a flash in a
pan you know I will make a commitment to
this you know you are more than welcome
with you to return and so this doesn't
have to be the end if you don't want it
to be and of course we're not even sure
what this is and what is an end but but
if we wanted to gather again to talk
then we can and so in that sense you
know I I I hope to continue to draw on
you know a sense of patience in myself
and faith you know and an affirmation of
the of the
to to tune as deeply as possible into
this understanding of the relationship
between connection and disconnection and
knowing that knowing that the the final
answer is not to present itself to me so
quickly
I would like to jump in so I rather like
frames and I like precision and I like
specificity so I'm going to throw some
words and some precision on this so I
wanted to relate some of the comments
that you said to some of the comments
that Leslie had brought out now you use
the metaphor of the dance which but I
really like because the dance is a very
caring trusting act and you also made
reference to this frame that sort of
billows out - as for far a point as we
can imagine mm-hmm I want to relate that
also to the point at the beginning of
this discussion which was you know how
do we feel trust with other people
especially if we can't use our
pre-existing frames or if we try to
simply sit in silence how without
knowing the particular case of a another
person can we feel held and supported in
a space with that other person so I
think that one of the plausible goals
about the process being undergone here
which I would put in terms of world
transition and world making is how do we
that's a good word here how do we
establish a process for world making
that ensures that we feel held and cared
in as many spaces as possible such that
we feel open enough to allow our
fullness to come out without it being
perhaps you know stepped upon by
somebody else who isn't quite on the
same page you live in a place now where
there are silly different worlds and so
many different frames that it can become
hard to engage in that sort of same page
openness that say cultures of another
time would have been able to do when we
could realistically believe that
everybody sort of had a shame a shared
belief set that's a little bit harder
for us to accomplish right now I think
it makes sort of the problems of
nihilism a lot more present right you
met you mentioned a point earlier which
was this we don't have to do anything
which I think is precisely the problem
actually the fact that there are some a
plausible frames of reference that we
don't have to do any one thing like
that's the problem how do we structure
world that both makes sure that as wide
an array of people possible are included
and cared for while all still providing
some sort of impetus for action right
because the action is what translates a
world into reality and that process is
next necessarily going to include and
denying some other people right there's
going to be some people who don't get to
speak in a particular world so yeah so
that's a lot of thoughts that I have
about this that the clarity that I would
bring to this is that I think the
process really is transitioning from the
world from from a postmodern world of
multiple perspectives where we all sort
of have to be on our toes about each
other and to not really have trust in
our immediate interactions to and then
from there move into one where we all
can sort of participate in world
building processes as part of a
community which i think requires a lot
of flexibility right because we have to
be able to come into a space where there
is no prior shared meaning and then to
sort of pick one up
right off the bat and then I think
there's necessarily an element of fear
and horror that comes in that right if
you don't know the particularity z' of
people then how do we know that we can
trust those people and if they're you
know Michael you were mentioning some
apprehension some anxiety about this
sort of intuitive leap into this novel
space there is a lot of fear and even
horror that comes when there isn't an
established world there isn't some sort
of reliable ground there to catch us
so yeah the dialectic of like faith and
fear I think is a particularly important
one in this process and then I think the
goal for that we're grappling with that
particular dialectic is the
establishment of a way of having
communities that enables us to world
make on a case-by-case basis in a way
that includes care for as many people as
possible
yeah like you did okay good
I know I said a lot there so I just
wanted to check in and make sure that
everything was clear or if anybody
needed clarifying I like it because I
realized when I listen to that that I
I'm more used to more local groups um
you know I lived in a community for
quite a few years where you know I lived
with people seven days a week and it was
very intimate and I and I in my normal
life
I have my home life and my work life and
my friends and they're all local and I
have some zoom calls with friends
elsewhere but I'm used to a certain type
of culture of communicating and so I
realized that if I want to be part of a
more of a world culture I have to get
used to Oh quite a big range of other
people's ways of communicating and what
what's meaningful to them which is not
going to be the same as what's
meaningful to me and I me I probably
need to do some of the work for feeling
cared for so
I don't rely on other people caring for
me in certain ways because if they're
all in different countries and cultures
and situations they're gonna have very
different ways and I do think I need to
learn to expand to be around more people
I think we all it would be a great skill
for all of us because you know we're
facing a world defining situation and
having more skills that working with
more diverse groups sounds a really good
idea and one of the one of the things
that are valuable the tools that are
useful in in meeting with different
groups what you both said you know made
a lot of sense to me and you know it was
easy to agree with what you were saying
from what I could make sense of it and
and that there's a couple of you know
questions that came up for me which is
something like this I think when you're
talking about the fear and horror of
coming into an interaction where there's
no established ground and I think I
recognized in myself that if is this a
kind of interaction where there's no
established ground because if it's very
easy for me to feel grounded here and
that there are a lot of other situations
where there is an established ground
where I feel really quite at sea and so
I was trying to work out is that is that
because this is more like just being
comfortable with groundlessness and
falling and that's where I'm comfortable
or is it because I can bring my own
ground here and but also in terms of
care you know I feel like it was really
useful to hear Leslie use kind of
thinking through some of your own
process there because it didn't occur to
me really to doubt that there was a kind
of a care in this interaction which was
easy to connect to and I think it's
because I didn't feel that any care here
was anchored to something and that there
a kind of a sense of trust or faith
isn't that for me in an interactional
sense yeah I was beautifully put pen
yeah really beautifully articulated I
was working for something similar
wondering why it was that I approached
the conversation with such implicit
trust for everyone and I thought it's
because of the ground that I'm bringing
and understanding that we have some
shared something coming in whether it's
the seekers mentality or some some
unspoken Center the world that we all
share but for whatever reason this is my
first time ever doing something like
this so but I felt the implicit trust
from the beginning but also its valuable
Leslie to hear you know that need for
care it makes a lot of sense yeah I just
wanted to voice that I I felt the the
care from the beginning maybe the
enthusiasm when we first began as well
fed into that sense of Khoury frame yeah
I think one thing about care for me is
that I like to test it a bit um that I
don't
I felt I feel good about all of you
and you all seem worthy people to be in
dialogue with but sometimes I like to
poke it a bit and it helps me you know
like I try and you know I'm trying to
encourage my husband and I'd have more
conflicts because they're more they're
very fruitful of some new things coming
out and that when we're too nice to each
other we don't we don't have that the
same contact as when we're prepared to
poke and be uncomfortable with each
other and so again with that whole thing
of the the different
Beks being uncomfortable is a great tool
for me to break into something new and
yeah so that's great I like to hear that
that sounds very wise to me and it makes
a lot of sense to be masked earlier
where are you um we're trying to query
where we could see the positive and the
negative in our lives
mm-hmm what were you going to say yes
okay oh it just said that that sort of
the trickster impulse again you know to
kind of that that idea of poking you
know where can we take this hmm
trickster to something that seems to
come up that would be very very fruitful
to do fully embrace this trickster push
at the edges kind of character in going
about this sort of world transition
world making project as I was listening
to you speak I was thinking that a
useful exercise could be something like
send people a narrative that is
seemingly horrifying but that there is
some sort of insight some puzzle that
they have to grab grab a whiff is that
as you know Ben and Jessica mentioned
like there's not really an immediate
sense that Oh groundlessness is amongst
us or frameless Ness is here you really
have to push people to that point the
way to do that really well is with
something that seems sort of horrifying
or grotesque on the face of it but that
once it's contextualized in the
appropriate kind of way comes to be seen
as oh just a fun little game that was
here to teach all along so something
that could I think really effectively do
what you're trying to accomplish in this
kind of context just to get a whole
bunch of people who have never talked to
each other before and then get them to
before even introducing each other say
the most grotesque or horrifying thing
that comes to their minds like that
would be terrifying for everybody and
would surely push them to the edge of
their frame yeah no doubt
and interestingly so my expressing the
most loving thing
Oh contacts of strangers that could yes
yeah well it's uh we're getting to the
boundaries what do we meet there you
know do we meet connection actually when
we fall together his stories do we meet
this connection there's like hey maybe a
thought for another time but the
groundless mystical participatory we
love is not far away from that set of
characterizations
you know maybe deeply deeply found there
you know John's notion of the reciprocal
opening the dialogical opening as being
a process enabling of love or revelatory
of love what
the the the this lovely dynamic of
groundlessness but then being held there
you know what is a friend of mine once
had a DMT experience where he an image
he saw at one point was of himself and
his friends in a circle holding hands
looking up towards the void a void in
this case as being he kind of horrifying
destabilizing abyss yet nevertheless
arms linked a kind of relational care
and love as an interesting it's an
interesting dynamic the horror and the
presencing of horror the presencing of
love the transgress
of boundaries associated with both each
our routes very different routes in some
sense I almost topologically this is a
very abstract project they almost
topologically like a kind of shape
that's a figure it's like a like a
multi-dimensional figure of eight you
know you can be going down you can be
going up but but the trans framing in
the middle and what reconstitutes from
the ash that the affectation of life the
the for itself and the connection we
find in that we are of that it's you
we can speak about it metaphorically I
so one final thing to say for me well I
won't be the final thing but Dan just
going back to you I also like precision
- hey but I like I like this
relationship between expanse and
precision yeah which is so which I know
you did too and and also having to hold
my hands back do you know that sometimes
it's gonna be more precise and perhaps
it ought to be and sometimes more
expansive than perhaps it would be
helpful to be and we never can fit the
world into one box at one period of time
you know so have to be humble with
respect to that perhaps we can each of
us in turn express some closing thoughts
as we move towards the closing of our
time together here today I my experience
for the last couple of hours was one of
feeling
closings and openings within myself and
and it really tied in was what we ended
up talking about of um you know like the
good and the bad and the bad and the
good and all of that and that
that just something about just the being
willing to participate in the closings
and openings and sometimes the openings
being more than I want like you said to
him and sometimes the you know like that
the detailed part is too detailed and
sometimes the opening is too open for me
or for anyone else and that but there's
something about the dynamic of allowing
all of that that is really helpful and I
feel the left was feeling quite
satisfied with experiencing that with
you all so thank you yeah a good time I
would say that I had a lot of fun in
this interaction it is easy to get into
a space of the play when there's like
not too much of a serious point which I
like it's nice to sort of sit back and
just ride the waves and see what comes
out and you have the topics that we
covered are all stuff that I'm having a
great time thinking about right now so I
liked getting the insight from the way
that those ideas were interacted with
amongst everybody yeah also feeling very
satisfied right now
yeah I go with them satisfied you know
as well and as you know in a good couple
of hours for me and you know nice to
hear you'll and nice to hear from you
all and you know be at a distance and
participate and be able to speak with
you as well no so thanks a lot I really
enjoyed finding the through art through
the personal exploration and talking
about our current life situations
finding the through-line
that we all seem to share the the sort
of the collective shadow we're all
battling it was really and I mean
certainly I've seen that same thing
mirrored with the people in my life
there's a lot of finding the polls of
yourself and trying like heck to get
that equilibrium and so yeah that was
really those really fruitful to feel
that and there's a certain feeling of
connection that is just beneath all this
more of a more of a feeling than
something that can be verbalized but
certainly felt was gratifying regret
fighting to be here with you all
or
the QA process where
kind of what Tim Tim described it the
structure the opposing calls coming
together always it was like kind of
reaching in the middle which seemed to
me is a pure exposure of our nudity and
I think yet this times art types of
clash where like we some people give the
best and some people give their worst so
it's like the self is really making a
breakthrough and we can really observe
if we look closely the reality in a
weight with much more exact lenses as we
see it in the normal system where
everything is kind of covered with with
the confined structures which are
working in certain dynamics which are
not interrupted but now we kind of had
to stop and look around and some people
are getting freaking kale some people
you know different people interact in
different way and yeah I think these dis
this conversation and my perspective
kind of mimicked all the dynamics of the
situation started in a very abstract way
of not knowing again kind of went
evolving to something beautiful and I
really liked how it bloomed and thank
you very much for sharing it was
beautiful for me yeah beautiful thank
you for being here I really appreciate
it and what I'll do is I'm sensual and
email to give you an option to sign up
to the next conversation before I put
that publicly because there is a limit
obviously for the number of people we
can have in here I mean I'm interested
to experiment with up to about 20 and
we'll see how that goes it will be a
different experience but there is there
does seem a cap and I also want to open
this up so that these conversations can
be held without me needing to hold them
and that way that way we can extend more
invitations you know but slowly with
that process and it doesn't have to be
through here you know obviously I
encourage everyone well I'll just say
that that much they encourage everyone
for whatever but not for whatever that's
too much of a that's to open on the
frame that's more that whatever is
basically uh you know it's kind of like
I've got a few podcasts out and between
the lines
I think it's hum don't know if it's
clear but
as
an action was so good oh you're still
there I was doing well I signed the
emails off with phrase discernment on
the way
this is not a this is not a statement of
relativism you know it's a statement of
appropriate openings in closures and not
to be flippant about what those openings
and closures are for each one of you and
your individual lives it's my hope that
the world can participate in more
transformative conversations and that
means that more people are going to have
to take the initiative to hold them this
may be a multi-decade kind of process
and it's not just about conversation at
least verbally but yeah I'm super
grateful to spend all this time with you
and I I hope and look forward to
crossing paths again hopefully not
before too long or before too long yeah
all right so okay then I will end this
cool now and I encourage you all to I
mean what I'm gonna do is probably do a
bit of stretching a bit of breathing and
I find that the process of exiting
interactions like this is is quite
important because the the jump can be
quite significant so yeah I encourage
you to feel into the continuity even in
the face of the discontinuity of me
pressing this end meeting may be the
best way to do it actually would be to
say that this then is is now over and I
invite you all to hang up yourselves how
about that that is probably the right
way to do it so thank you so much
see you soon thank you thanks Tim cheers
bye everyone bye folks